<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Judaica DH at the Penn Libraries</title>
    <description>Judaica Digital Humanities at the Penn Libraries is a robust program using digital technologies to augment and transform the ways in which to explore Jewish history. By experimenting with platforms, tools, and methodologies, we deepen and broaden our understanding of Jewish history, texts, cultures, ideas, and experiences.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2020 11:00:12 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2020 11:00:12 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Columbia University Libraries Hosts Scribes of the Cairo Geniza Event</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On &lt;a href=&quot;http://scribesofthecairogeniza.org/&quot;&gt;Scribes of the Cairo Geniza&lt;/a&gt;, thousands of people around the world come together on the Zooniverse platform to assist professional researchers through the remarkable potential of crowdsourcing. Last week, project team members at Columbia University Libraries brought members of the crowd together in a special presentation led by Emily Esten and Michelle Chesner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the COVID-19 pandemic kept us from hosting in-person events, we combined our efforts for a global Geniza transcribe-a-thon via Zoom. Columbia University Libraries hosted a &lt;a href=&quot;http://scribesofthecairogeniza.org/&quot;&gt;Scribes of the Cairo Geniza&lt;/a&gt; transcribe-a-thon on Tuesday, April 7. You can watch a recording of the event on our YouTube channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just before noon, participants joined the chat to say hello from all over the world. Penn Libraries’s Judaica DH Coordinator, Emily Esten, started with a project introduction, walking participants through the history of the Cairo Geniza, the project’s goals, and what’s next for the site. Michelle Chesner, Norman E. Alexander Librarian for Jewish Studies at Columbia University Libraries, discussed the history of Columbia’s Jewish collection, and the Cairo and European geniza fragments included in the project. that are from Columbia’s Judaica collection. Chesner and Esten then took Q&amp;amp;A from participants, answering questions about the history of Geniza collections, other #DHJewish projects, significance of project questions and so much more &lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around the one-hour mark, Esten provided a walkthrough of the transcription interface, demonstrating various toolbars, keyboards, and text modifiers for use. Chesner later shared her screen to transcribe a line, and also demoed the sorting workflow. We had over sixty participants join us throughout the conversation, from all over the world! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though this event  came to an end, the hard work of the project continues on the web. Volunteers can always participate on their own time at &lt;a href=&quot;http://scribesofthecairogeniza.org/&quot;&gt;scribesofthecairogeniza.org&lt;/a&gt;, and we hope to have more events like this in the future! Thank you to the Rare Book &amp;amp; Manuscript Library and the Digital Scholarship Unit at Columbia University Libraries; the Digital Scholarship unit and Schoenberg Institute for Manuscript Studies at Penn Libraries for hosting this event. And special thanks to Michelle Chesner, Emily Runde, Nicky Agate, Peter Magierski, and Mitch Fraas for their assistance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resources mentioned during the event:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hebrew and Judaica manuscripts from Columbia University’s Rare Book &amp;amp; Manuscript Library on &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/culhebrewmss&quot;&gt;Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/ldpd_11566596_000/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Ketubah fragment from present-day Iraq&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information on &lt;a href=&quot;https://johannes-obadiah.org/index.html&quot;&gt;Johannes of Oppido&lt;/a&gt;, a Catholic monk who converted to Judaism in 1102 CE.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A Columbia manuscript with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://exhibitions.library.columbia.edu/exhibits/show/hebrew_mss/congregants/x893_j725&quot;&gt;manicule&lt;/a&gt; (not geniza). You can also check out our blog post on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh/talking-the-talk-manicules-a71c7a9a3df6&quot;&gt;Geniza manicules&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1zdbLJ6aZioZL4S-yGMS-SrVhz3eqwrA7fkNggPMQLJg/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;spreadsheet of all fragments with art-related tags&lt;/a&gt;, curated by Zooniverse user angelamarie&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Resources for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/1026/1111822?page=1&amp;amp;scrollToLastComment=true&quot;&gt;learning more about the Cairo Geniza&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A video for &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/ak1HzrIprCA&quot;&gt;how to transcribe on Scribes of the Cairo Geniza&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://repository.upenn.edu/cairogeniza/&quot;&gt;repository for Scribes of the Cairo Geniza-related materials&lt;/a&gt;, including datasets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An example of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/1029/416415?comment=694488&amp;amp;page=1&quot;&gt;conversation on the Talk Boards&lt;/a&gt; (you can read that discussion in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh/talking-the-talk-chad-gad-yah-d1ce7abadf0a&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;, too!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please consider joining us on&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://scribesofthecairogeniza.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scribes of the Cairo Geniza&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;to participate in unlocking the secrets of one of the greatest archives of the middle ages! Interested in hosting your own transcribe-a-thon? Check out our&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://judaicadh.github.io/cairogeniza/resources/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;organizing guide and resources&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;or contact judaicadh@gmail.com.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/p/fdca1b3400a6&quot;&gt;View original.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exported from &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; on April 14, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2020-04-14-columbia/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2020-04-14-columbia/</guid>
        
        <category>Scribes of the Cairo Geniza</category>
        
        <category>Presentations</category>
        
        
        <category>Scribes of the Cairo Geniza</category>
        
        <category>Presentations</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>DataDeepDive: Passover</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In this series, we take a deep dive into the Talk boards tags to look at how volunteers classify the fragments. You can read an overview of our Talk boards tags in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh/reviewing-sorting-phase-data-talk-board-tags-d0c0b90dc43c&quot;&gt;Sorting Phase Data review&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/tags/passover&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Passover&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;is one of the most widely celebrated Jewish holidays, commemorating the emancipation of the Israelites from slavery in ancient Egypt. The name comes from the Hebrew &lt;em&gt;Pesach&lt;/em&gt;(“to pass over”), referring to when G-d passed over the Jewish homes during the final of the Ten Plagues of Egypt. It begins on the 15th day of the Hebrew month Nisan, and lasts for seven or eight days. (In 2020, that means it begins at sundown on April 8 and ends Thursday evening on April 16.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people associate Passover with the Seder, the ritual feast that marks the beginning of Passover. It’s usually celebrated at home with family, friends, and community members. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/search?query=Haggadah&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;haggadah&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is the book used during the Seder on Passover, retelling the story of the Exodus from Egypt. There are many options for a haggadah, varying in commentary, illustrations and translations.
From left to right: Subjects &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/subjects/11619897&quot;&gt;11619897&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/subjects/11596803&quot;&gt;11596803&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/subjects/11583880&quot;&gt;11583880&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018, we used the power of the crowd to create a Haggadah out of fragments from the Cairo Geniza. This patchwork haggadah invites people to look critically at the texts that they use on the holiday. You can check it out on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sefaria.org/sheets/105137?lang=bi&quot;&gt;Sefaria&lt;/a&gt;! Combining fragments tagged by volunteers, we ordered the fragments according to their place in the seder. You can read more about that process in &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh/sederscribes-1866981146e6&quot;&gt;an earlier blog post&lt;/a&gt;. You’ll notice that the text may differ from modern Hebrew, and that some of the fragments are written in Judeo-Arabic, Judeo-Persian, and other languages!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After candles are lit and everyone is seated at the table, the Passover Seder can begin. The first step, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/tags/kadesh&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kadesh&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, is when the attendees recite the Kiddush.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/subjects/11614566&quot;&gt;Subject 11614566&lt;/a&gt;: ENA 2945.20, Library of the Jewish Theological Seminary&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/tags/urchatz&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Urchatz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is when attendees wash their hands in preparation. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/tags/karpas&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Karpas&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is the dipping of a vegetable into salt water, symbolizing the tears the Jews shed during their servitude.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/subjects/11596834&quot;&gt;Subject 11596834&lt;/a&gt;: ENA 2150.34, Library of the Jewish Theological Seminary &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/subjects/12502537&quot;&gt;Subject 12502537&lt;/a&gt;: ENA 2434.2, Library of the Jewish Theological Seminary&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During Passover, one cannot eat &lt;em&gt;chametz&lt;/em&gt; (leaven bread) and instead eats &lt;em&gt;matzot&lt;/em&gt; (unleavened flatbread). Three matzot are stacked in the middle of the Seder table. When the Seder Leader calls out “ &lt;strong&gt;Yachatz&lt;/strong&gt;”, the three matzot are taken out, shown to all, and the middle piece broken in half to be hid until later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/tags/magid&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Magid&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the story of the Exodus from Egypt is read aloud. This section is also known for the Four Questions and Four Sons, explaining why these traditions are upheld to this day.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/subjects/11583874&quot;&gt;Subject 11583874&lt;/a&gt;: Halper 213, University of Pennsylvania, Hebert D. Katz Center for Advanced Judaic Studies Library, Cairo Genizah Collection&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/tags/rachtzah&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rachtzah&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, attendees once again wash hands for a ceremonial cleansing, while reciting the traditional blessing.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/subjects/12499510&quot;&gt;Subject 12499510&lt;/a&gt;: ENA 696.10v, Library of the Jewish Theological Seminary&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During &lt;strong&gt;Motzie&lt;/strong&gt;, the blessing for the matzot is recited, followed by the &lt;strong&gt;Matzah,&lt;/strong&gt;a second blessing and the eating of a small piece of the bottom matzoh. Next is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/tags/maror&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maror&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, where the bitter herbs are eaten to remember the affliction of the Jewish people from sorrow, persecution, and suffering of life in bondage. And in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/tags/korech&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Korech&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the dipped maror and matzoh are combined in a sandwich.
Subject 11606694: ENA 1966.6, Library of the Jewish Theological Seminary&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, it’s time to eat during &lt;strong&gt;Shulchan Orech!&lt;/strong&gt;The meal customarily starts with a hard boiled egg dipped in salt water, a sign of mourning. Eating isn’t officially done until &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/tags/tzafun&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tzafun&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, where the broken matzah from Yachatz returns to the table to be eaten by all the participants.
Subject 11609304: ENA 2322.13, Library of the Jewish Theological Seminary&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next is &lt;strong&gt;Bareich&lt;/strong&gt;, the grace after meals is recited — the Birkat Hamazon. The cup of Elijah (and sometimes Miriam) is set out for his arrival. During &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/tags/hallel&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hallel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the remainder of the Psalms of Praise are read aloud.
Subject 11609306: ENA 2322.14, Library of the Jewish Theological Seminary&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the conclusion of the Seder, the leader calls out &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/tags/nirtzah&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nirtzah&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; — next year in Jerusalem! Attendees sing songs and enjoy each other’s company. The last song of the night for many is “Chad Gad Yah”, popular with children for its simplicty. We’ve written before about the fragment below as part of our &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh/talking-the-talk-chad-gad-yah-d1ce7abadf0a&quot;&gt;#TalkingTheTalk&lt;/a&gt; series!
Subject 11606300: ENA 1697.12, Library of the Jewish Theological Seminary&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chag-pesachsameach&quot;&gt;Chag Pesach sameach!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;check-out-more-tags-or-start-your-own-by-participating-in-scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza-on-zooniverse&quot;&gt;Check out more tags or start your own by participating in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scribesofthecairogeniza.org/&quot;&gt;Scribes of the Cairo Geniza&lt;/a&gt; on Zooniverse!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh&quot;&gt;Judaica DH at the Penn Libraries&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/p/ab131243d77c&quot;&gt;&lt;time&gt;April 7, 2020&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh/datadeepdive-passover-ab131243d77c&quot;&gt;Canonical link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exported from &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; on April 14, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2020-04-07-passover/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2020-04-07-passover/</guid>
        
        <category>Scribes of the Cairo Geniza</category>
        
        <category>Data Deep Dive</category>
        
        
        <category>Scribes of the Cairo Geniza</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>NCPH 2020: #DHJewish: Sharing Judaica with the Internet and Beyond</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The following transcript and slides were part of a Twitter chat at National Council for Public History, March 2020.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to #DHJewish: Sharing Judaica with the Internet and Beyond! I’m going to talk for a bit about building digital projects for Jewish and non-Jewish audiences, and efforts to connect w/ offline community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m Emily Esten, the @judaicadh coordinator at @upennlib. I manage the collaboration between digital scholarship &amp;amp; special collections depts. to integrate digital technologies into the ways we study Jewish history. #NCPH2020 #s36 &lt;a href=&quot;https://judaicadh.github.io/&quot;&gt;https://judaicadh.github.io/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Part of my efforts since starting this position has been bringing a public history lens to @judaicadh. Specifically, I’m interested in how to bridge the various communities our projects attract (Jewish/not, academic/not, online/not) and Penn’s materials. #NCPH2020 #s36&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our largest project, Scribes of the Cairo Geniza (scribesofthecairogeniza.org), is a multilingual crowdsourcing project on @the_zooniverse to classify and transcribe fragments of medieval and premodern manuscripts from the Cairo Geniza. #NCPH2020 #s36&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We DON’T presume basic knowledge of Hebrew, Jewish history, or manuscripts. The vast majority of volunteers are NOT Jewish. (Anecdotally, people who follow along via social media usually are.) Check out our community demographics here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh/who-are-the-genizascribes-5b58915227a6&quot;&gt;https://medium.com/@judaicadh/who-are-the-genizascribes-5b58915227a6&lt;/a&gt; #NCPH2020 #s36&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This ends up with a lot of exciting conversations on the Talk boards, w/ volunteers who can share knowledge talking with those who do not. Read this convo about a ketubah (marriage contract) &amp;amp; the practice of marrying before Passover. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/subjects/21707788&quot;&gt;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/subjects/21707788&lt;/a&gt; #NCPH2020 #s36&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve also started working on more in-person events outside the university, bringing in community members to engage with library materials online. #NCPH2020 #s36 &lt;a href=&quot;https://njjewishnews.timesofisrael.com/pitching-in-to-unlock-mysteries-of-cairo-geniza/&quot;&gt;https://njjewishnews.timesofisrael.com/pitching-in-to-unlock-mysteries-of-cairo-geniza/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, I worked with the children &amp;amp; adult learning programs at a local temple, talking about the project in conversation with crowdsourcing &amp;amp; Jewish history. Working with kids who read Hebrew characters has been SO rewarding! #NCPH2020 #s36 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.library.upenn.edu/blogs/libraries-news/probing-time-capsule-cairo-geniza-adath-israel-synagogue&quot;&gt;https://www.library.upenn.edu/blogs/libraries-news/probing-time-capsule-cairo-geniza-adath-israel-synagogue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s easy to think about this type of engagement with a crowdsourcing project — there are built-in opportunities for participation and involvement! How can we generate similar connections with digital repositories and exhibits that we’re building? #NCPH2020 #s36&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In what ways can we do this that engage with the existing #dhjewish &amp;amp; online Jewish communities that look for/use these resources? And what ways can we support the offline transition for disseminating these projects? #NCPH2020 #s36&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&amp;amp; finally, one of the things we emphasize as part of @judaicadh is that the digital is diasporic. Bringing together Jewish history in a digital environment is so important because people &amp;amp; materials are dispersed. How can we best integrate that into our work? #NCPH2020 #s36&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As our program grows in collections and conversation, I hope @judaicadh grows into a space that centers participation with Jewish communities on &amp;amp; offline. #NCPH2020 #s36 &lt;a href=&quot;https://penntoday.upenn.edu/news/gifts-arnold-and-deanne-kaplan-penn-libraries-enrich-judaic-scholarship-and-digital-humanities&quot;&gt;https://penntoday.upenn.edu/news/gifts-arnold-and-deanne-kaplan-penn-libraries-enrich-judaic-scholarship-and-digital-humanities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OK, any questions? &amp;amp; check out my fellow #NCPH2020 #s36 panelists at @charliehersh, and @TheOtherRBG for more content!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh&quot;&gt;Judaica DH at the Penn Libraries&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/p/e7c98b37ed74&quot;&gt;&lt;time&gt;March 31, 2020&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh/ncph-2020-dhjewish-sharing-judaica-with-the-internet-and-beyond-e7c98b37ed74&quot;&gt;Canonical link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exported from &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; on April 14, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2020-03-31-ncph2020/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2020-03-31-ncph2020/</guid>
        
        <category>Scribes of the Cairo Geniza</category>
        
        <category>Conferences</category>
        
        
        <category>Scribes of the Cairo Geniza</category>
        
        <category>Presentations</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Who are the #GenizaScribes?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Who are the #GenizaScribes, the thousands of volunteers who participate in &lt;a href=&quot;http://scribesofthecairogeniza.org&quot;&gt;Scribes of the Cairo Geniza&lt;/a&gt;? As we move forward with our project, we decided to ask the #GenizaScribes community questions to learn how we can best support and grow our volunteer base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our goals were to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify the current demographic of #GenizaScribes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand participant motivation in the project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Receive feedback about the project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The survey was open from Tuesday, December 12, 2019 through Monday, January 13, 2020, and available only through direct email via Zooniverse. Thus, only volunteers who had registered with Zooniverse, participated in the project &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; once, and have not opted out of receiving project-related emails were eligible to participate. We received 205 survey responses (5% of email recipients, 2% of all participants). All responses listed below are in aggregate, in descending/alphabetical order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zooniverse performed a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.zooniverse.org/2015/03/05/who-are-the-zooniverse-community-we-asked-them/&quot;&gt;similar study regarding engagement in 2014&lt;/a&gt;, from which we borrowed several questions. Zooniverse has grown its user base and expanded its project offerings significantly since that survey, but provides a baseline for how to interpret our responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to those volunteers who completed the survey! As always, you can join us in classifying and transcribing fragments from the Cairo Geniza at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scribesofthecairogeniza.org/?utm_source=newsletter&amp;amp;utm_campaign=announce6mar19&quot;&gt;scribesofthecairogeniza.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Some entries have been grouped and edited for clarity (ex.: USA, U.S.A., and United States of America all referring to United States of America.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**This response was removed early on in the survey due to a typing error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How old are you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our community is made up of people of all ages! Due to some typing errors, we realized after the fact that the 60–69 age demographic was entirely missing from our responses. While this may not be completely accurate to our respondents, it gave us a good sense of the age range of participants.
A pie chart of the ages of survey respondents&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To which gender identity do you most identify?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.zooniverse.org/2015/03/05/who-are-the-zooniverse-community-we-asked-them/&quot;&gt;2014 survey&lt;/a&gt;, our user sample skews female — good work towards achieving gender parity in the Zooniverse! This question was included in the survey as an open-ended question, meaning respondents could &lt;a href=&quot;https://nebula.wsimg.com/4c27929f438a2dee7c064e1c5b2a7b51?AccessKeyId=B6885E9DB42D0C2EAC6F&amp;amp;disposition=0&amp;amp;alloworigin=1&quot;&gt;describe their gender identity in the way that best fits them&lt;/a&gt;.
A pie chart of gender identifies over respondents shows a majority of participants identify as female.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In what country do you currently reside?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The responses also seem to match the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.zooniverse.org/2015/03/05/who-are-the-zooniverse-community-we-asked-them/&quot;&gt;2014 survey&lt;/a&gt;, which found significant participation from the United States of America and the United Kingdom. However, we are excited to see representation from 27 different countries around the globe! Our survey results include seven countries that were not represented in the 2014 survey — Austria, Finland, Tanzania, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Hong Kong, Philippines, and Spain — though we know from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://daily.zooniverse.org/2015/02/25/zooniverse-global-challenge/&quot;&gt;2015 Zooniverse Global Challenge&lt;/a&gt; that the site has global coverage and sees visitors from those countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are particularly excited to see significant engagement from Israel. We know we have had many participants through community engagement efforts by our partners at the University of Haifa. We would like to strengthen our engagement efforts in countries where Arabic is an official or national language, none of which are represented in our survey demographic (outside of Israel).
A pie chart of countries involved highlights the top countries in which survey respondents reside: USA, UK, Canada, Israel, France, Australia, Italy, Finland, Germany, Sweden, Tanzania, The Netherlands, and Argentina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the highest level of education you have completed?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of participants who identified as having completed some post-graduate school training was significantly higher than expected. For comparison, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.census.gov/data/tables/2017/demo/education-attainment/cps-detailed-tables.html&quot;&gt;educational attainment data&lt;/a&gt; from the U.S. Census Bureau in 2017 reported that less than 15% of American adults have a professional degree that required study beyond a four-year bachelor’s course. Combined with the professional data from below, we can infer that many of these positions may require graduate degrees.
95% of #GenizaScribes have had experience in higher education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is your employment status?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over half of our community is employed (either full- or part-time), followed by a significant number of retired volunteers.
A pie chart of the employment status of survey respondents&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is your current (or most recent) profession?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From academics to zoologists, we have a wide range of professionals represented in the #GenizaScribes. The most frequent words in these responses were teacher (15), manager (14), librarian (11), computer (7), and engineer (7).
A word cloud of free-response answers to the question provides an in-depth look at professions of #GenizaScribes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which languages do you know?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2019, &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh/update-launching-phase-2-224c2a3a8bb4&quot;&gt;we launched our multilingual interfaces&lt;/a&gt; in Hebrew and Arabic. 73% of survey respondents identified as Native English speakers, but 36% of all respondents had some knowledge of Hebrew and 14% of volunteers had some knowledge of Arabic. While our engagement with native speakers of Hebrew and Arabic speakers was low in this survey, we plan to continue promoting the project to these linguistic communities.
A column chart notes that the majority of #GenizaScribes are Native English speakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also asked respondents what other languages they know in addition to Arabic, English, and Hebrew. #GenizaScribes are quite the polyglots! In addition to the three languages of our project, 85% of respondents noted basic proficiency in at least one additional language. The top six languages included in these responses were French, Spanish, German, Italian, Latin, and Russian. Jewish diaspora languages like Aramaic, Yiddish, Ladino, and Shuadit were also represented in responses. We hope this information could help drive future multilingual crowdsourcing and digital humanities projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where did you hear about our project? (select all that apply)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lots of ways people hear about Zooniverse and our project specifically! Knowing that these respondents opened an email from Zooniverse, it seems unsurprising that previous participation in Zooniverse projects led to them joining Scribes of the Cairo Geniza. But we are also glad to hear that our work on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/judaica_dh/&quot;&gt;social media&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://judaicadh.github.io/cairogeniza/press/&quot;&gt;press coverage&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/iAP4zgK_jT8&quot;&gt;public presentations&lt;/a&gt; by members of our team have been successful in bringing in new volunteers.
#GenizaScribes are engaged participants in the Zooniverse!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which workflows have you participated in the project?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of survey respondents have participated in the sorting workflows. This tracks with our site stats, where over 93% of 9,407 volunteers have classified fragments into Hebrew or Arabic script. The sorting workflow is easier and does not require any language proficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over half of our survey respondents have participated in the transcription workflows at least once, with more transcribing Easy Hebrew fragments than Easy Arabic fragments. This is much higher than our site stats, where 601 volunteers have transcribed Hebrew fragments and 131 volunteers have transcribed Arabic fragments, as of December 20, 2019. But we can expect that those who responded to the survey are more engaged in the project.
Most survey respondents participate in the sorting workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you have posted in the forums/Talk, which of the words below describe the purpose of your contributions? (select all that apply)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;518 volunteers total have participated on the Talk boards — about 5% of our volunteer base overall. A large segment of those volunteers is represented in the survey, often using these social spaces to discuss findings from participation. That makes sense based on our involvement with those spaces, where we answer questions and engage with the research term to learn more about fragments in the project.
A bar chart of purpose of Talk boards contributions shows us that most people want to discuss findings!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which of the following words describe your view of participating in the Zooniverse? Please select all that apply.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consistent with the findings of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.zooniverse.org/2015/03/05/who-are-the-zooniverse-community-we-asked-them/&quot;&gt;2014 survey&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/0909.2925&quot;&gt;2009 study&lt;/a&gt; exploring the motivations of citizen science volunteers, people want to contribute to progress! Combined with the answers of the following question, volunteers are very interested in the content of this project specifically, and the ability to learn about Jewish studies, Hebrew language, and manuscript collections.
Interest and the desire to contribute drive most #GenizaScribes to participate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What has been your favorite part of participating in Scribes of the Cairo Geniza?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Respondents shared many personal anecdotes — we have highlighted some of the survey responses below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“As a novice sofer I was fascinated to see the school book lesson pages, particularly the one with facial doodles…”
“Brushing up on Hebrew, seeing history/research in action!”
“Discovering astounding pieces of texts. Some of them are among the images I use as wallpaper on my computer.”
“Felt great to finally transcribe something — even just one line!”
“Finding ‘doodles’ or little figures along with the text. It’s amazing to see the the corrections or edits of the original scribes. It’s like looking into our ancestors’ minds.”
“I found it very challenging in a good way, it really made me focus on the visuals/structure of the letterforms to attempt to sort accurately.”
“I had read the book Sacred Trash by Adina Hoffman so it was exciting to help sort some of the fragments I had read about.”
“I had to leave college before accomplishing my terminal degree, so having the opportunity to contribute in a small way to a project involving papyrus and translation touched on a lifelong dream. My immense gratitude to those who made it possible for me to participate.”
“I love using it in class with my students! It was an easy way for them to feel connected to Jewish history and better understand the everyday of academic research.”
“Learning to distinguish daily life vs “high” versions of the scripts”
“Reading old Hebrew and Aramic and try to figure out what they are speaking about.”
“Reading words written by people a long time ago, and helping document them, possibly contributing to understanding how groups of people created meaning for themselves. And also in a strange way, I liked being immersed in a succession of often quite beautiful images (script).”
“Seeing older (even ancient) texts. Usually I’ve been working on projects with writing/info from the 20th century.”
“Seeing writing from hundreds of years ago and thinking about the people who created those documents — this is such a cool glimpse into their lives”
“…Like most people, I will never handle an ancient piece of writing, only see pictures or film of it. But digitally manipulating these documents and helping scholars eventually interpret them makes me feel a very real connection to the source material, the people who wrote it, and the time they lived in.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you have lost interest in Scribes of the Cairo Geniza, please indicate your reason(s) why.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volunteers being busy, noting project difficulty, and unfamiliar with Hebrew and/or Arabic were the most common factors for leaving the project. We received good feedback about clarifying project goals, providing more assistance with transcription, more regular updates from our team, and ways to optimize the sorting workflow for mobile use. Several volunteers had forgotten about the project over time, and were glad to receive a reminder!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-become-one-of-the-genizascribes-yourself-join-us-in-sorting-and-transcribing-geniza-fragments-at-scribesofthecairogenizaorg&quot;&gt;👉 Become one of the #GenizaScribes yourself! Join us in sorting and transcribing Geniza fragments at scribesofthecairogeniza.org!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh&quot;&gt;Judaica DH at the Penn Libraries&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/p/5b58915227a6&quot;&gt;&lt;time&gt;February 5, 2020&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh/who-are-the-genizascribes-5b58915227a6&quot;&gt;Canonical link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exported from &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; on April 14, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2020-02-05-genizascribes/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2020-02-05-genizascribes/</guid>
        
        <category>Scribes of the Cairo Geniza</category>
        
        
        <category>Scribes of the Cairo Geniza</category>
        
        <category>Announcements</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Princeton Geniza Lab Hosts Scribes of the Cairo Geniza Transcribe-a-thon</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On &lt;a href=&quot;http://scribesofthecairogeniza.org&quot;&gt;Scribes of the Cairo Geniza&lt;/a&gt;, thousands of people around the world come together on the Zooniverse platform to assist professional researchers through the remarkable potential of crowdsourcing. This week, project team members at Princeton University brought members of the crowd together in-person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Princeton Geniza lab hosted a &lt;a href=&quot;http://scribesofthecairogeniza.org&quot;&gt;Scribes of the Cairo Geniza&lt;/a&gt; transcribe-a-thon on Tuesday, November 12. Encouraging volunteers to become long-term citizen historians is one of our key project goals. But our larger mission — recovering unknown chapters of the history and culture of medieval Jews, Muslims, and others in the Middle East and North African region— is something in which everyone can participate. Needless to say, the project welcomes volunteers from all backgrounds, not just those with prior knowledge, experience, or foreign language proficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students, faculty, staff, and members of the public arrived at Jones Hall on Tuesday morning with their laptops ready. Penn Libraries’s Judaica DH Coordinator, Emily Esten, started with a training session, walking participants through the history of the Cairo Geniza, the project’s goals, and how to transcribe fragments using the site. Fueled by caffeine, snacks, and the motivation to contribute to ongoing scholarship, participants worked for four hours on transcribing and sorting fragments. &lt;strong&gt;Working together, 26 volunteers transcribed 37 Hebrew subjects and 48 Arabic subjects, and sorted 46 subjects for later transcription.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though this transcribe-a-thon came to an end, the hard work of the project continues on the web. Volunteers can always participate on their own time at &lt;a href=&quot;http://scribesofthecairogeniza.org&quot;&gt;scribesofthecairogeniza.org&lt;/a&gt;, and University of Pennsylvania volunteers can join at the next Geniza transcribe-a-thon at Van Pelt Library on December 5, 12:30–1:30 PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please consider joining us on&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://scribesofthecairogeniza.org&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scribes of the Cairo Geniza&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;to participate in unlocking the secrets of one of the greatest archives of the middle ages! Interested in hosting your own transcribe-a-thon? Check out our&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://judaicadh.github.io/cairogeniza/resources/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;organizing guide and resources&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;or contact judaicadh@gmail.com.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh&quot;&gt;Judaica DH at the Penn Libraries&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/p/42340bb45b40&quot;&gt;&lt;time&gt;November 13, 2019&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh/princeton-geniza-lab-hosts-scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza-transcribe-a-thon-42340bb45b40&quot;&gt;Canonical link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exported from &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; on April 14, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019-11-13-princeton-geniza-lab/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2019-11-13-princeton-geniza-lab/</guid>
        
        <category>Scribes of the Cairo Geniza</category>
        
        
        <category>Scribes of the Cairo Geniza</category>
        
        <category>Announcements</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>#MCN2019: Cultivating Community with the Cairo Geniza</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The following transcript and slides were part of a lightning talk at the Museum Computer Network conference in San Diego, November 2019.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*iusdLDk47HgWTJys_Mj7lQ.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every day when I go to work, before I check my email or start coding or talk to my supervisor — the first thing I do is dive into the chat forums, or Talk boards. I’m not slacking off — I’m the project coordinator for Scribes of the Cairo Geniza, a crowdsourcing project led by Penn Libraries and the Zooniverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*bm_xnx6OiYlzrGm-0FvB_w.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project seeks to identify, classify, and transcribe medieval Hebrew and Arabic fragments once located at a historical synagogue in Cairo, Egypt. These fragments are now located in libraries around the world, from St. Petersburg to Cambridge to Los Angeles, and virtually all of them have been digitized. Over two years, we’ve mobilized nearly 8,000 people in reviewing over 50,000 fragments. Our site includes Arabic, Hebrew, and English interfaces for the world to participate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*WHmcQW9X1Z77UHArhvwX1A.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project in itself could be an entire lightning talk, but what I want to focus in on here are the Talk boards. That’s where I spend a lot of my time. Most Talk boards for crowdsourcing projects are used for troubleshooting issues, or specific help questions. But the volunteers in this project have made use of the Talk boards to create their own classifications systems, work together to teach each other, and generate conversations about Jewish history and culture, linguistics, and the work of libraries in the preservation of materials. We have participants commenting on the Talk boards in all three languages of our project. And with all of these people talking to each other, it’s made me think about what fostering public participation in research really looks like once you have a crowdsourcing project up and running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*wYz33cTIBGw1y81GNlKZdw.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I want to show you two examples of what I mean. For volunteers who don’t read Hebrew or Arabic, visual features on these fragments are often striking — like this alama, outlined in the red rectangle in the corner. This visual characteristic is important to understanding and identifying fragments, but there aren’t nearly enough of them for our research team to make it a task or question in the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*yFQerEmqR5ramxU4M1zQeQ.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But volunteers started noticing an alama here or there, and one volunteer contacted me, asking if they could have a list of all the fragments in the project. So we said yes, handed over our data, and in about two weeks they came back with a tag, a definition for our glossary, and a collection of fragments they identified as definitely having an alama or possibly having the feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*HN6zz92fHT73M7XruWX-Ow.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the takeaway from this moment was that it demonstrated user participation in project-level research, trusting engaged volunteers with tasks — helping them on their way to achieving researcher status. They’re asking questions like a historian, so why not help them on their way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*aIjzNZxsck-KNUOHelhogg.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other side of things, sometimes volunteers are interested in questions our team hasn’t spent a lot of time thinking about. Volunteers generated dozens of tags related to art, doodles, decorations, or drawings. And one volunteer was so impressed by the variety of artwork, she asked others to join her in creating a collection. So I reached and supported her, sharing all of these tagged fragments — and she, in turn, developed item-level metadata describing what she saw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*T9iwi4tsPfS3WMNMYJ0Kuw.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as she did this, and wanted to promote what she found, our team shared the fragments &amp;amp; descriptions on social media — which wound up back in the hands of our project partners, amazed by things in their collections they hadn’t known existed before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*TnlaMUBuQ5tRAlyBrLJS6g.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which takes me to the other side of the spectrum: opening your collection to answer the research questions you intended is one thing, but following user-generated research can help spark new interests that we haven’t even begun to ask as teams or institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*utDfmsMM8JonwJ77b9DDQg.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So crowdsourcing projects are certainly not new to museum professionals at this point, and they are a great space for public participation in research. But having this open dialogue space, where people feel empowered to write in their languages, ask questions, and take on responsibility in a project supports that work is what takes this unique project to another level. It’s helped our project grow into a space of learning, communication, and collective ownership of the data that’s created. It takes a lot of investment on our team’s end to be responsive, in-the-know, and OK with sharing things in-progress, but it’s also incredibly rewarding to see how volunteers can inform, develop and transform a project over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh&quot;&gt;Judaica DH at the Penn Libraries&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/p/eaf5182c28cd&quot;&gt;November 7, 2019&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh/mcn2019-cultivating-community-with-the-cairo-geniza-eaf5182c28cd&quot;&gt;Canonical link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exported from &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; on April 14, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/mcn-2019/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/mcn-2019/</guid>
        
        <category>Scribes of the Cairo Geniza</category>
        
        <category>Conferences</category>
        
        
        <category>Scribes of the Cairo Geniza</category>
        
        <category>Presentations</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Explore Robert Singerman's Judaica Americana</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Judaica DH at Penn Libraries is excited to announce that Robert Singerman has donated to the Penn Libraries the draft of the full text and copyright to his revised second edition of &lt;em&gt;Judaica Americana&lt;/em&gt;, the award-winning, magisterial two-volume bibliography of American Jewish publications before 1900. His draft of the second edition, including a Supplements section, and a dataset based upon it, is now discoverable in ScholarlyCommons, the University of Pennsylvania’s open access institutional repository: &lt;a href=&quot;https://repository.upenn.edu/judaica_americana/&quot;&gt;https://repository.upenn.edu/judaica_americana&lt;/a&gt;. Both files now are available to researchers, book trade specialists, genealogists, and bibliographers with the information they need to mine this invaluable resource.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This draft deposit is the first step towards an interactive digital publication of the second edition of &lt;em&gt;Judaica Americana&lt;/em&gt; (JA2) to appear within the framework of Penn’s Judaica Digital Humanities program. JA2 will incorporate the monographic entries from the foundation (JA 1990) bibliography and the supplemental materials into an open, full-text searchable database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Singerman’s first edition, issued in 1990 in two volumes was sponsored by the Center for the Study of the American Jewish Experience, Hebrew Union College-Jewish Institute of Religion, and published by Greenwood Press as part of the Bibliographies and Indexes in American History. In it, Singerman, identified just over 6,500+ monographic and serial publications, presented with meticulous bibliographical descriptions, classification explanations, and holdings information, i.e., the names of collections where copies are known to be held. His bibliography authoritatively chronicles American Jewish book production from the 17th century to the beginning of the twentieth century. The second edition contains an additional 3,000 entries. The revised total now consists of a still expanding sum of approximately 9,500 entries. Taken as a whole, Singerman’s bibliography provides extensive and authoritative documentation of American Jewish communal activity and growth before 1901.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are profoundly grateful to Robert Singerman, Emeritus University Librarian, University of Florida for entrusting us with his extraordinary work and to Emily Esten, Penn’s Judaica Digital Humanities Coordinator, for all of her time and expertise re-formatting and transforming the text into a dataset and interactive platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh&quot;&gt;Judaica DH at the Penn Libraries&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/p/a33c8721707d&quot;&gt;&lt;time&gt;October 30, 2019&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh/explore-robert-singermans-judaica-americana-a33c8721707d&quot;&gt;Canonical link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exported from &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; on April 14, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019-10-30-explore-judaica-americana/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2019-10-30-explore-judaica-americana/</guid>
        
        <category>Judaica Americana</category>
        
        <category>Digital Second Edition of Judaica Americana</category>
        
        
        <category>Digital Second Edition of Judaica Americana</category>
        
        <category>Announcements</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Birds of the Cairo Geniza</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/GenizaScribes?src=hashtag_click&quot;&gt;#GenizaScribes&lt;/a&gt; have been collecting artwork of birds from the Cairo Geniza. Here is a Twitter thread of some of our favorite fragments.
From the Story of the Dove in Kali lah wa-dimma, about a raven carrying a rat over a lake. T-S Ar. 40–9, Genizah Research Unit, Cambridge University Library Is that a bird clutching a mouse in the upper left corner? ENA 3306.2, Library of the Jewish Theological Seminary Two birds in the same prayer book. ENA 2321.3 &amp;amp; 2321.6, Library of the Jewish Theological Seminary A 439–1, The University of Manchester Library&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;-see-more-beautiful-fragments-by-participating-in-scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza-on-zooniverse-&quot;&gt;👉 See more beautiful fragments by participating in &lt;a href=&quot;http://scribesofthecairogeniza.org&quot;&gt;Scribes of the Cairo Geniza on Zooniverse&lt;/a&gt; !&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh&quot;&gt;Judaica DH at the Penn Libraries&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/p/caf79368ffbe&quot;&gt;&lt;time&gt;October 4, 2019&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh/birds-of-the-cairo-geniza-caf79368ffbe&quot;&gt;Canonical link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exported from &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; on April 14, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019-10-04-birds-cairo-geniza/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2019-10-04-birds-cairo-geniza/</guid>
        
        <category>Scribes of the Cairo Geniza</category>
        
        
        <category>Scribes of the Cairo Geniza</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Talking the Talk: Join</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this series we honor the contributions made on the Zooniverse Talk boards for our project,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza?source=post_page---------------------------&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scribes of the Cairo Geniza&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;. Talk is a way for citizen scientists on Zooniverse to converse with one another and experts on the different material they are working on, ask questions, and explore new insights. Each week we will feature a talk conversation that we love. Thanks for the participation #genizascribes!&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/subjects/30753597&quot;&gt;Subject 30753597&lt;/a&gt;: Gaster Printed 174–1, Gaster Printed 174–2, The University of Manchester Library&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;chavi-ny-haggadah-printed&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;@Chavi-NY:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/tags/haggadah&quot;&gt;#haggadah&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/tags/printed&quot;&gt;#printed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ev111--subject-30753597--30753598--30753650-all-feature-the-same-page-from-different-copies-of-the-same-haggadah-publication-hebrew-border-cover_page&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;@ev111&lt;/strong&gt; : &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/subjects/30753597&quot;&gt;Subject 30753597&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/subjects/30753598&quot;&gt;30753598&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; 30753650 all feature the same page (from different copies) of the same Haggadah publication . &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/tags/hebrew&quot;&gt;#hebrew&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/tags/border&quot;&gt;#border&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/tags/cover_page&quot;&gt;#cover_page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/subjects/30753598&quot;&gt;Subject 30753598&lt;/a&gt;: Gaster Printed 175–1, Gaster Printed 175–2, The University of Manchester Library &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/subjects/30753650&quot;&gt;Subject 30753650&lt;/a&gt;: Gaster Printed 213–1, Gaster Printed 213–2, The University of Manchester Library&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;stefriegel--a-complete-page-of-this-subject-can-be-seen-here-&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;@stefriegel&lt;/strong&gt; : A complete page of this subject can be seen &lt;a href=&quot;https://winners-auctions.com/en/content/collection-5-haggadot-vienna-binding-synagogue-jerusalem&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; :&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://winners-auctions.com/en/content/collection-5-haggadot-vienna-binding-synagogue-jerusalem&quot;&gt;A Collection [5] of Haggadot from Vienna with Binding of the Synagogue in Jerusalem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-view-the-conversation-here--&quot;&gt;👉 View the conversation &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/1029/1042974?source=post_page---------------------------&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;  .&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;read-more-talk-conversations-or-start-your-own-by-participating-in-scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza-on-zooniverse&quot;&gt;Read more Talk conversations or start your own by participating in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scribesofthecairogeniza.org/?source=post_page---------------------------&quot;&gt;Scribes of the Cairo Geniza&lt;/a&gt; on Zooniverse!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh&quot;&gt;Judaica DH at the Penn Libraries&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/p/b6abba4bb616&quot;&gt;&lt;time&gt;August 1, 2019&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh/talking-the-talk-join-b6abba4bb616&quot;&gt;Canonical link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exported from &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; on April 14, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019-08-01-talking-the-talk/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2019-08-01-talking-the-talk/</guid>
        
        <category>Scribes of the Cairo Geniza</category>
        
        <category>Talking the Talk</category>
        
        
        <category>Scribes of the Cairo Geniza</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Talking the Talk: Donkey Drawings</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this series we honor the contributions made on the Zooniverse Talk boards for our project,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scribes of the Cairo Geniza&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;. Talk is a way for citizen scientists on Zooniverse to converse with one another and experts on the different material they are working on, ask questions, and explore new insights. Each week we will feature a talk conversation that we love. Thanks for the participation #genizascribes!&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/subjects/30295467&quot;&gt;Subject 30295467&lt;/a&gt;: Ar. 338–1, Ar. 338–2, The University of Manchester Library&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;@judaicadh&lt;/strong&gt;: possibly connected to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/subjects/30295602&quot;&gt;30295602&lt;/a&gt;
Subject 30295602: Ar. 447–1, Ar. 447–2, The University of Manchester Library&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;@stefriegel&lt;/strong&gt;: Possible composition of the two drawings: It could be the head of a donkey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;@judaicadh&lt;/strong&gt;: Oh, yes! I wonder if we’ll find more of the donkey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;--view-the-conversation-here--&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;👉&lt;/em&gt;  View the conversation &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/judaicadh/scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza/talk/1029/1042974&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;  .&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;read-more-talk-conversations-or-start-your-own-by-participating-in-scribes-of-the-cairo-geniza-on-zooniverse&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Read more Talk conversations or start your own by participating in&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scribesofthecairogeniza.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scribes of the Cairo Geniza&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;on Zooniverse!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh&quot;&gt;Judaica DH at the Penn Libraries&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/p/f6a54eefc1e1&quot;&gt;&lt;time&gt;July 18, 2019&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@judaicadh/talking-the-talk-donkey-drawings-f6a54eefc1e1&quot;&gt;Canonical link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exported from &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; on April 14, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019-07-18-talking-the-talk/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2019-07-18-talking-the-talk/</guid>
        
        <category>Digital Humanities</category>
        
        <category>Scribes of the Cairo Geniza</category>
        
        <category>Talking the Talk</category>
        
        
        <category>Digital Humanities</category>
        
        <category>Scribes of the Cairo Geniza</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
